Hi, welcome back to our at-home retreat.
And again, thank you Xiaoping for
translating.
This is session number eighteen,
and we have called it "One Wheel, Two
Lives."
And the picture I chose was a
human being sort of becoming like a
superhero.
Now, sometimes I use superhero pictures
to represent a person who's very good
and inspires other people, but in this
drawing we are talking about a human
being who would like to be reborn in the
deva realm where people look
like superheroes, but then they have
terrible deaths there.
So we've been talking
about sections of the Wheel of Life, and
we kind of felt--it kind of feels to you
doesn't it?--that one Wheel of Life from
one o'clock to twelve o'clock ... that should
be
one lifetime.
But then we learn it's more
complicated than that.
And we saw that
link number eleven, which is rebirth, and
link
number twelve, which is aging and death,
just two links can be a whole lifetime.
So a very famous question comes up in
the ancient books: how many lifetimes
does it take to get through the whole wheel
one time?
And it's not a just a
philosophical question.
We have to go
through these next two classes ... we have
to talk about how many lifetimes can be
in one wheel, because we're going to find
out something amazing about that wheel.
And that's that if you look at
a Wheel of Life, it's going like this, then
that will trigger another set of links,
and then this one will trigger another
set of links, and then there will be some
links ... three there, three there, three
there, three there ... a few weeks in
your wheel of life weeks.
It can be
triggering many lifetimes, and many
lifetimes can go into one life.
I like to
think of it like the inside of a fine
watch--a mechanical watch.
So
we're going there--we'll talk
about that watch later.
But first let's
just see: how can just two lifetimes fit
in one wheel?
So let's go to the text and
it says de na hlar kyewa tabu la tsun na
(DES NA LHAR SKYE BA LTA BU LA MTSON NA,)--
let's take the case of a human
being who wants to be born as a deva,
like a pleasure being.
Well, first
we have and then ... de ko na ...
(DE KHO NA ...)
...la mongpay ma rikpa
(...LA RMONGS PA'I MA RIG PA)--
first you have ... de
ko na la mongpay ma rikpa means @tattva; you
don't understand @tattva.
@tattva means "the
way the world is."
Again, let's go back to
the kitchen, to the first moment after
the wife walks in the kitchen.
She
doesn't say anything; she just wants a
hug.
And then suddenly her husband blurts out,
"You're so stupid!"
Then what does she say?
[I'm not stupid--you are stupid!]
No, that's later.
That's link number two.
What's number one?
[I didn't do anything!]
Yeah, "I didn't do anything, and he's yelling
at me!"
Yeah, "I didn't do anything; he yelled at
me!"
That's link number one.
It's called
"misunderstanding."
She doesn't realize his explosion is
coming because she yelled at her kids
last week.
So, one act of misunderstanding in the
kitchen, it can throw--project--a whole
other lifetime, and in the example here,
marikpay wang gi (MA RIG PA'I DBANG GIS)--that
misunderstanding in
the kitchen, hlay kyewa pen che kyi kye ne
...
(LHA'I SKYE BA 'PHEN BYED KYI SKYES NAS ...)
...nyong gyur gyi le (...MYONG 'GYUR GYI LAS)--
it throws... it
triggers a special kind of karma.
Now,
karma can be divided countless ways.
In
fact our Mixed Nuts translator group
is translating several books called
all the many ways you can divide karma.
But, there's a very famous division into
three kinds of karma.
Number one: tong...
(MTHONG...)
...gyur kyi le (...'GYUR GYI LAS)--means karma
which is so powerful that you will see
the result in this life before you die.
Second: kye ne nyong gyur gyi le
(SKYES NAS MYONG 'GYUR GYI LAS)--karma
which will create your very next life.
Then what's called shen la nyong gyur gyi
le (GZHAN LA MYONG 'GYUR GYI LAS)
means karma which will create all or
many lives after the next life.
So in this case, the book is talking...
the lam rim (LAM RIM) book is talking about
kye ne
nyong gyur gyi le--you're going to ... you're
creating karma which will throw your
very next life.
And the example here is a
life as a deva or a pleasure being.
Now I
have to change my story, okay?
Because you
cannot be born as a pleasure being from
yelling at your husband.
So she must have
come in the kitchen and said, "Honey,
you're the most special person in my
life," because he gave her a big hug.
But
actually, she should say, "I didn't do
anything and he gave me a hug?"
So she ...
she doesn't understand.
The hug she got
from her husband is coming from hugging
her kids last week.
So she's saying
something nice, "Oh, I love you!
Thank you
for the hug, honey!"
But still she's saying it
because of link number one: she doesn't
really understand.
So without understanding the hug came
from a seed in her mind from giving
her kids a hug last week, she reacts in a
positive way and says, "I love you, honey.
Thank you!"
And she plants a new seed.
Where?
Fifty dollars.
More exact.
Where?
Where does she plant
the seed?
Tim?
No.
She plants the seed on the
first half of link number three.
Okay?
That's where she plants her seed.
Then der kye na chi marung nyam du mon lam...
(DER SKYES NA CI MA RUNG SNYAM DU SMON LAM...)
...sok kyi dunpa chepa ni
(...SOGS KYIS 'DUN PA BYED PA NI)--
and then later
she says, "Wow!
I made some good karma--I
was nice to my husband.
I pray that good
karma will make me a deva in my next
life."
And in this example, that's arming
the karma at link number eight.
It's like the
water on the seed.
dunpa de nyi che ru...
('DUN PA DE NYID CHE RU...)
...tsunpa ni (...BRTZON PA NI)--
and then if she feels that wish
more and more, it becomes almost like
obsession with her, "Oh, that good karma
should make me a pleasure being in my
next life."
Then she's putting fertilizer--link
number nine--on that karma, also.
And
because of those two--water and
fertilizer--the karma that she planted in
the kitchen at link number two, it becomes
a
very, very powerful, fat seed ready to
break open.
And we call it... here it says
chi kar ('CHI KHAR)--in the moment of her
death,
right, in the last moment of her
awareness
of this world, those wishes to
go to a certain future, they make the
good karma seed fat. de nyi pen nge su chepay
le
(DE NYID 'PHEN NGES SU BYAS PA'I LAS)--
and that seed becomes definite: it will
open into a pleasure being's rebirth.
So,
our author summarizes: if you think about
it, we've had like two and a half thrower...
throwers?
Archers.
Two and a half.
Number
one, she misunderstood her husband.
two, but she gave him a very beautiful
hug.
Number three, in that moment she
imprinted a seed on her mind.
Now, so
that's kind of three links, and then
three more links are like the factory.
she misunderstands...
well let's say she has a feelings about
the seed, really.
She wants them...
she's
doing like coffee meditation where that
seed should open.
First coffee
meditation, stronger meditation--coffee
meditation, and then the seed is fat and
ready to open.
Those six links--three
archer links, three links which make the
seed ready to explode--those six of the
twelve links are happening in the first
life.
de ne chi mar hlar kye
DE NAS PHYI MAR LHAR SKYE)--and then that
seed
breaks open and she goes into a new life,
and she becomes that pleasure being, deva.
We call it deva or temporary pleasure life.
It can last for a million years, and it's
very, very pleasant and you look like
Iron Man or Superwoman, or something.
But when you die,
you always go to hell.
"Oh, why?"
You burned
up all your good karma.
So we think it's
like something you should avoid--that
kind of deva rebirth.
They are just
having fun, they don't try to improve
themselves, they don't learn more, they
kill their old good karma.
It's like very
wealthy children in this world.
Oftentimes, they they spend their whole
life using money without working.
chi mar...
(PHYI MAR...)
...hlar kyewa na (...LHAR SKYE BA NA)--so
let's say she's
reborn like she wished.
So what links are going to happen in the
second life?
ming suk (MING GZUGS)--to the body and
mind entering the mom's womb.
Number four,
link number four--the body and mind entering
the mother's womb.
Then link number five, her
ears, eyes, nose--they are forming.
Link
number six, because of those sense organs,
she will make contact with the outside
world.
Then automatically, link number seven--
she will start to have pleasant
experiences and she will start to have
unpleasant experiences.
And four, five, six,
seven--those four links and you can kind
of throw in half of her link number three,
too (conscousness)--
they are going to turn into kyewa (SKYE BA)
and...
...ga shi (...RGA SHI)--they're going to turn
into link eleven
and link twelve.
They are a whole life--
those four, or maybe five.
Yeah, and the
whole life is the two links: birth, and
aging and death.
Okay, so we have six resulting links.
chi ma hlay ten de la dzokpa te
(PHYI MA LHA'I RTEN DE LA RDZOGS PA STE,)
those six links are finished in the
deva birth.
So, we had six links in the
first life as a human, and six links in
the second life as a deva.
And this is
the way in which two lifetimes can be
finished in one wheel.
But I ask you to think about something.
And this is a little deeper.
Is it
possible that the karma she plants in
one life is not watered for a few more
lives--like the seed is just sitting there
...
Is it possible you could plant a seed today
and it will
take three lifetimes before that seed
gets watered?
Is it possible to plant a
seed today or have a seed... there's a seed
in Siberia, in Russia--it's a special flower.
They found one in the ice, which has been
there for thirty-one thousand years.
And
they planted it, and they put water on it,
and it grew a flower after thirty-one
thousand years.
So is it possible that
it might take more wheels before it opens?
We have to think about it.
But in today's
example, six links in the first life, six
links in the second life--twelve links in
two lifes.
Now there's a special
expression in Tibetan that you should
know, if you want to go deeper.
By the way, if you don't want to go
deeper, go get a pam she (SPAM BSHAD), pam
she.
It's a special Tibetan word called pam
pam she means go find a teacher
who didn't have much training, and
they'll say, "You know, be nice!"
"You know,
do it... do your @manis--@om mani padme hum--and
everything will be okay."
If that's enough
for you, then you don't need this lam rim,
okay?
But, I'm trying to get you to understand the
inside of the clock.
How does each piece
work?
Because to change that clock--@mar...
...mahatha...
for $50.
[killing point] Yeah!
You have to know the strike
point.
If you want to--it's a terrible
example, but it's in the scripture--if you
want to kill a human in two seconds, like
those kung fu masters, cut this vein right
here and the person has
to die.
You cannot fix it.
They have
to die in two minutes.
I have a friend, he
was building a house, he fell down, then a
nail scratched him here.
And he was standing
next to his wife,
and he died in two minutes.
And she's... she
couldn't do anything.
Okay, so... we want to
kill the wheel, so you have to understand
the anatomy of @sansara.
And where's the
exact place you have to cut... cut your
suffering?
So that's why we're doing all
this detail, okay?
So anyway, that word I
wanted to say tendrel tsar chik
(RTEN 'BREL TSAR GCIG)--it
means one time through the twelve... one
time through the twelve.
I didn't say "wheel."
I said one time through the twelve--we
don't know which twelve, and we'll talk more
about it.
We'll talk about it later.
Okay, last thing today.
ngen dro tabur tsun na
(NGAN 'GRO LTA BUR MTSON NA,)--
Okay that was with taking a good
rebirth.
So let's talk about a bad
We call... ngen dro (NGAN 'GRO) means "lower
realms"--three kinds: animal, hungry ghost,
hell.
okay tabur...
Now he says, "Let's talk about
a bad rebirth."
lendre la mongpa marikpa
(LAS 'BRAS LA RMONGS PA'I MA RIG PA)--
again it starts with misunderstanding
how karma works.
But in a deeper misunderstanding where
you just say, "I don't believe it at all."
Then you
don't feel like you have to do good
things to other people; you can just do
bad things.
So if your misunderstanding
is that bad, you will kill people, you
will lie to people, and you will collect
sok (GSOG) means you will "collect" bad karma.
Then that has its own water, its own
fertilizer, in your mind.
gong gi rik dre
(GONG GIS RIGS 'GRE)
means "Hey, and the rest is the same as I
told you before with the good karma."
And
that completes session eighteen.
Tomorrow we're
going on to can you have three lifetimes
in twelve links?
Can you finish a set of
twelve in three different wheels, almost--
three different lifetimes?
And we'll talk
about that one tomorrow.
Don't turn your mind off, you know.
Don't say, "This is too complicated!" okay?
You went through twelve years or sixteen years
of
school.
At the end, you could do very
complicated mathematics, and very
complicated science, and maybe you could
write complicated things from your
language classes.
But nobody taught you how to die.
Now you
don't... you may not be a mathematician in
your life, you may not write books or be
a scientist--and that happens to a lot of
us--and that means you didn't need those
twelve years.
But to spend a few days
learning how to die, which you have to do,
I think it makes sense, okay?
So see you
at class nineteen.
Thank you, and thanks Xiaoping
for translating.